<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian merchant described in a sermon at first design'd for a private audience, now humbly dedicated to all the merchants of the city / by William Gostwyke.</title>
            <author>Gostwyke, William, 1650-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11806055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11806055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49447</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41587)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49447)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 495:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian merchant described in a sermon at first design'd for a private audience, now humbly dedicated to all the merchants of the city / by William Gostwyke.</title>
                  <author>Gostwyke, William, 1650-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XIII, 45-46 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:49447:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49447:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Chriſtian Merchant</hi> Deſcribed in A SERMON.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49447:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49447:2"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Chriſtian Merchant</hi> Deſcrib'd in a SERMON At Firſt Deſign'd for A Private AUDIENCE, Now Humbly Dedicated to all the Merchants of the CITY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM GOSTWYKE,</hi> Rector of <hi>Purley</hi> in <hi>Berks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> M DC XC VI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49447:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49447:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Chriſtian Merchant.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St.</hi> MATTH. 13. 45, 46.</bibl>
               <q>Again, The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a Merchant-man ſeeking goodly Pearls: Who when he had found one Pearl of great price, he went, and ſold all that he had, and bought it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>again,</hi> we here firſt meet with, is rather an Introductor to the Text, then an Integral part of it; yet gives us to underſtand, that this is another Parable of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's, added to the former, more amply, and clearly to repreſent, and illuſtrate the Nature, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Kingdom of Heaven. Another, and ſo conſequently, that there is no danger in our knowing too much of our Duty to God, or our Intereſt in him. And that it is but a Miſtake of ſome men's, that Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is the only Mother of Piety and Devotion. Another Parable, that is Similitude, or Compariſon. For ſo St. <hi>Mark</hi> is well render'd, <hi>Whereunto ſhall we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mark 4. 30.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49447:4"/> 
               <hi>liken the kingdom of God: or with what Compariſon ſhall we compare it?</hi> Of theſe the Uſe is very frequent in the Scriptures of both Teſtaments. Whether it were, that a readier Attention, a clearer Perception, a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Impreſſion, a firmer Retention, or all theſe at once were wrought, or won by them, eſpecially when explain'd or apply'd; ſo it was, that very often of old when a Prophet was ſent on an Important Errand, it was reveal'd to him in a Viſion, and to be deliver'd by him in a Parable. And of our Bleſſed Saviour, the ſame Evangeliſt aver's in a few Verſes following, <hi>that in many ſuch Parables he ſpake the word</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 33.</note> 
               <hi>to the people;</hi> and adds, <hi>as they were able to hear it;</hi> that is, as was moſt intelligible, and withal moſt profitable for them, ſaith the learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on the place. Of this in the Text the two Terms, or Extremes are differently taken, and underſtood. Some take them for the Kingdom of Heaven on the one Hand, and the Pearl of Price on the other. As if it had been ſaid, The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a Pearl of great Price. By the Kingdom of Heaven meaning the Happineſs of Heaven; as the Phraſe often imports, eſpecially in Promiſe, as in St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and elſewhere. And by the Merchant-Man, the good Chriſtian continually ſeeking, till he make it ſure. Others take the Kingdom of Heaven indeed for the one, but for the other extream, the Merchant-man: Reading the words as they run, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a Merchant-man.</hi> Theſe meaning by the Kingdom of Heaven, the whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49447:4"/> Church of Chriſt Militant here on Earth, but to be triumphant hereafter in Heaven: as the words ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignify, eſpecially in Parable, as here. Where then, the Enallage has a favourable Aſpect either to the whole Church, put for every ſingle Member of it: or to the ſingle Merchant-Man, put for the whole Company, of which he is a Member. And by the pearl of Price purchaſed, the Happineſs of Heaven as before, gain'd. By the firſt account, the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heaven to a Chriſtian is like a Pearl of great Price to a Merchant-Man. By the Second, the Church of Chriſt in gaining Heaven is like a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Merchant-men purchaſing a Pearl of great Price. Or more particularly, and plainly thus. The good Chriſtian aiming hereafter at Heaven is like a Merchant purſuing his beſt Intereſts here on Earth. <hi>Senſus, duplex, &amp; uterque probandus.</hi> Both Sences are ſound, both good, and not unlikely both intended by our great Maſter, with whom it was very uſual in One Propoſition, to give us more points than one of Inſtruction. Of this Compariſon in this later ſence, to which my occaſions at preſent lead me, the Ground, or Foundation is the parity or likeneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Perſons here compar'd. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Chriſtian is very like a well accompliſht Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant. Indeed <hi>Omne ſimile eſt &amp; diſſimile:</hi> there is ſome odds and ſome advantage too, on the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſide, as ſhall be ſhewn; but in many things they meet, and agree. They ſeek alike, they find alike, alike they ſell all, to make a purſe, or one grand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49447:5"/> Purchaſe at laſt; that is, contentedly part with any thing of lower price, to get higher, till they can reach the Top, and compaſs the Sum total of their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs once for all. This parity to make appear—, I ſhall give you the beſt account I can of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in general; Divide it for clearer Proceſs into particulars; Compare the Chriſtian with him in each particular; and to make the Character a little fuller, touch on two or three of his many excellent Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and as I may, Apply.</p>
            <p>A Merchant then is a Vertuous, and Valuable Perſon, of great and uninterrupted Dealings, abroad, and at home, with deſign to make himſelf, and to make others happy. This I take the Merchant to be; And this with a very eaſie Turn is the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Vertuous Perſon, our Saviour here ſuppoſes him; in that he ſends the Chriſtian, not to correct, to cull, or curtail, but tranſcribe him. And ſuch, for the preſent, I ſhall ſuppoſe the Chriſtian to be. One that whatſoever things are honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, and of good report; if there be any Vertue, if any praiſe, as ſure enough there is; the Chriſtian is one that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſyllogizes, argues, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons himſelf into the Love, purſuit and practice of theſe things. Now to ſuppoſe him Vertuous, is to aſſert him Valuable; for Vertue is at leaſt the Baſis, if not the very Eſſence of all true worth and value. <hi>But beſides,</hi> as the World goes, there are ſome other things add to his Stature, and ſet him above many
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49447:5"/> others: as his Birth, and Breeding. Firſt his Birth. 'Tis not for every Block to yeild a carv'd Head; nor every common Stone a curious Statue. 'Tis not for every One to put himſelf upon this Office; nor take upon himſelf this Honour; but He that is call'd, and enabled of God, and good Friends. In other, and our own Nation too, they are the Sons generally of the better ſort that are dedicated to this generous Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy. And they had need of ſomething uncommon, <hi>ex traduce,</hi> and deriv'd down to them, that are to go through all parts, and upon the whole, make any thing conſiderable of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Chriſtian too</hi> as ſuch, is of a Noble Extract, of a Deſcent indeed Divine; not born of Fleſh and Blood, or of the Will of Man, but God: is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of the Family of Heaven, and near ally'd to the Ancient of Dayes there. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. His Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, Heir, and Joynt with Chriſt. And has a Seed remaining in him that he cannot Sin. A ſettled <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 1.</note> Principle that poſſeſſes him with a juſt ſcorn of any thing baſe, below, or unbecoming him. Won't ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to ſneak, and ſlave it to Sin and Satan from day to day as others do: But as a natural Genius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires him, with all that's great and good; and ſo worthy of his Anceſtors, and of himſelf.<hi>—Again, His Breeding.</hi> It has been ſaid a Poet may be Born, an Orator muſt be Bred: but without both, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, neither will be exquiſite. The Merchant in his Minority is grounded in Learning, and the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, from the beſt Authors, and by the beſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49447:6"/> At a hand is Curious, and in ſeveral of the Mathematicks made almoſt Maſter. And when bound Apprentice, that is, a Learner ſtill, He comes from Theory to Practice. He has thoſe ſpecial Rules ſet before him, that with common Care, he cannot fail in Buſineſs. His being Bound, by the way, he takes not for a trouble, much leſs diſparagement to him. There's no Man but is bound to ſerve his King, his Country, his Family, and Friends ſome way, or other. He's bound, but 'tis to One that's bound as well to him, and is to be as juſt and kind on the one hand, as he is true and tractable on the other. 'Tis at a time when he needs more Care took of him, than very likely he would take of himſelf: And when with many others to be looſe, might be to be for ever loſt. And 'tis but for a time, <hi>Deus dabit huic quoque finem,</hi> will have an end: he is not to have his Ears peirc't through to perpetuate it. 'Tis upon terms eaſie to him, his Maſter being more his Father, and his Service better than many others Freedom. And Advantagious to him; at anothers Expence to make himſelf a Man: and by the Trail of Pike to come to be the abler General. So that in a ſenſe, he's only bound to ſerve himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian has his training up in the Nurture, and Admonition of the Lord too. And as the Breaſt-Milk he firſt drew became good Bloud, and Spirits in him to his after-health, and ever better habit of Body: So the good Notions he then imbib'd, turn'd as in <hi>Timothy</hi> to Principles, and thoſe confirm'd by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49447:6"/> the Reverend Maſters of Aſſemblies enoble the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and Inclinations of his Mind, and enable him to every good word and work, that is, to the whole buſineſs of his Chriſtian Calling. Being timely told, <hi>'tis beſt to bear his yoke in youth:</hi> Now is the time, he <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 17.</note> ſets his ſhoulder to it. Takes his Baptiſmal Vow upon himſelf; enters the Liſts in his own Perſon; engages to flee youthful Luſts, and manfully fight under Chriſt's Banner. Now, 'tis, he's taught the Uſe of the Bow, and Buckler; the Weapons, and Way of War offenſive and defenſive. Now 'tis, he reſolves to know him, whom to know is Life Eternal; and to ſerve him, whom to ſerve is perfect Freedom. Now 'tis, that <hi>ſubacto, &amp; puro ſolo,</hi> in a broken, and contrite heart, he ſowes the Seed of Grace, in hopes of a plentiful and joyful Harveſt. Now buſineſs comes thick upon him, and he becomes a Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of great, and uninterrupted Dealings abroad, and at home. He ſeeks, he finds, he veiwes, he goes, he comes, he likes, he bids, he buyes, he takes home, he books down, he layes up: meets a new man, acts a new part, and ſells to Buy: that is, to do all this over again. And this all expreſt, or fairly intimat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the very Text. The many and various Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or rather Goods dealt in and for, by the many Eminent Merchants that are, are almoſt endleſs to inſtance and be particular in. Generally ſpeaking, they are conſiderable either for Bulk, and Quantity; or for Worth, and Value. Such as commend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Uſes and Neceſſities of the Moſt, or to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49447:7"/> the Exactneſs and Curioſity of the greateſt. Our preſent Merchant is for goodly Pearl: a thing well known here, in Sickneſs highly Cordial; in Health, as rarely Ornamental. With what he prudently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, he ſtill, and ſteadily goes on to the laſt. Seeks till he finds, then leaves not, till he buyes. He nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtarts aſide to Novelties he needs not, nor makes a ſtand in the midway as non-pluſt, nor of a ſudden gives off all, as if <hi>non compos,</hi> not maſter of his own Mind; but keeps his Courſe, and keeps his Pace, till he have gain'd his Point. Abroad he ſends as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as the Company agrees on't; oftener, if his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for ſupplies require it. And ſometimes goes himſelf, to ſee who, and how they do, he deals with; or the diſpoſe, or manage of what he deals in. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and hazards may ſurround, but neither can ſurpriſe him, who is prepar'd for the worſt that can come, come what will. At home between Export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Importing, and all the many requiſites to both ſucceſſively, or together; between Creditor and Debtor, keeping accounts, and clearing them, and in Chooſing the beſt time for all things, he is ſo took up, he has no leiſure to liſten to the Sirens of Temptation, or be taken with them.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian likewiſe has his full ſhare of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of as much Importance to him. Has fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Principles as before, while young, to learn, and make his own; in riper years, to make profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of, and put in practice; and from his own Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to Communicate at laſt to after-Comers, Has
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49447:7"/> Revelation to adore, and to believe; and Reaſon moſtly in other matters, to bring himſelf to be rul'd by. Has Truth to vindicate, and Errour to oppoſe. Has Prohibitions and Threats for his Fear to work, and naked Promiſe now, and then, for his Faith to live upon. Has Poſitive Inſtitutions; Natural, and Moral Line upon Line, and Precept upon Precept many, directed to him to Obey. A God in Heaven to know, and own; to Love, and Fear; to Serve, and Honour; to Truſt, and to delight in; to Pray to, and to Praiſe at all times. On Earth Men: Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours to be Subject; Equals to be Civil to; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours to ſuccour, help, and comfort. Has all Men to do all that for at all times, he could wiſh done himſelf at any time in any caſe of need whatever. And has himſelf to look to, and take care of; no ſmall Charge, no very eaſie task neither. He has, naturally ſpeaking, a reſty body to break, and keep under: a rambling Head, a wanton Eye, an itching Ear, a lawleſs Tongue, an open Sepulchre of a Throat, would ſwallow all that's offer'd, and an Heart deceitful above all things, to reduce to primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Uſe, and Inſtitution. He has a corrupt Mind to correct, and cultivate; vain Imaginations, vile Affections, a deprav'd Judgment, an obſtinate Will, many an oblique Wiſh, and Deſire, to take to task, and ſet to rights. Has a pack of Ruſſian, and Rude Paſſions within him to Collar, and keep in Irons, <hi>Né lanient ipſum;</hi> leaſt they pull the whole houſe upon his head. Has a World of Temptations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49447:8"/> him to eſcape, or overcome, or they will draw him in, and drown him in Deſtruction and Perdition. Has Diſappointments, Loſſes, and Croſſes to bear, and make the beſt of, that is, out of the Eater to get Meat, and Honey from the ſtrong. He has the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Appartments of a large Soul to furniſh, and the chief Repoſitory there to Enrich and Store with all the Vertues, and Graces of the Goſpel: and to keep all as bright and ſafe, as he would his Evidences for Heaven, and his Title to a bleſſed Eternity. Yet hitherto his way is tolerable, his work is pretty plain, and eaſie, he has not yet reſiſted unto bloud. But now, and then he meets with knots and difficulties extraordinary to deal with. Sometimes with Caſes that want a well-read Conſcience to inform him in: Sometimes with Intricacies that require the beſt. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Council, to bring him out of: Sometimes with Stones, and Rocks of Offence, which make him need a friendly hand to help him over. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he has a ſudden deſcent to make, is to come down from his own Will, and ſeeming Reaſon: to deny his own dear Self, perhaps in that, that's dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to him, and muſt ſtoop, and take up his Croſs. But moſtly his Way is Up-Hill, he is to grow in Knowledge, and in Grace: to forget things paſt: to paſs things got, and preſs on to a perfect Stature, and then to riſe from ſtrength to ſtrength until he come to <hi>Zion.</hi> This is what the good Chriſtian is to do, this is ſome part of it, for in this hurry, 'tis not one half that I can tell you. This is what the good
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49447:8"/> Chriſtian does, at leaſt, he does his beſt to do. What 'ſcapes his Hands he works out on his Knees: begs Pardon firſt, then Help of God: ſo doubles his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and regains his loſt ground. And this he does all Enemies, and Oppoſition to the Contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, The Fleſh flinching, the World frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Devil raging, the very Gates of Hell broke looſe, and rattling about his Ears. As one that's Deaf, he hears not; as one that's Dumb, he opens not his Mouth. Theſe and the like are the Goods he Merchant-like ſends out. Theſe, or in two Words, as one from Heaven Sums up a Bill of Lading, newly brought in thither, His Prayers, and Alms. Theſe he <note place="margin">Acts 10. 4.</note> continually caſts, <hi>as bread upon the waters,</hi> and perhaps <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 1.</note> before many days, perhaps after, however, whenever he moſt wants it, he finds return'd, and brought home to him, in the moſt ſuitable Mercies of God upon him. The View, he takes of the Holy Land, to which his Commerce lies, is like that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> from the top of <hi>Piſgah</hi> too; at diſtance, but brought near by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective of a lively Faith, that ſhews him things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible to others, things inconceivable to himſelf. His Timeing all things to advantage, as by good Advice, <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 13.</note> both makes the buſineſs eaſier he is to do, and makes the End the ſurer, he at firſt deſign'd. And that is</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To make himſelf, and to make others happy.</hi> The Merchant's none of thoſe, that Cloſet themſelves only to catch Flies; or that work only to be weary, or worſe purpoſe: but One that from the beginning propos'd to himſelf an End; and that end worthy of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49447:9"/> all his thoughts, his Cares, his Travel, and his Pains. He ſeeks as readily and far forth as any man; he'l find, or make a paſs <hi>per Mare, per Terras</hi> to the remoteſt <hi>Indies,</hi> or round the Univerſe, but it ſhall be for goodly Pearl, or what's as good. He that ſays this is mean or mercenary in him, reproaches all Mankind at once, as much as him. Who plants a Vineyard, or feeds a Flock for nothing? Or to look higher, What Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 7.</note> fights? What Scholar Studies? Or Courtier waits, but has preferment in his Eye? Nor without Reaſon, till a better Title to it, can be produced. 'Tis but <hi>Currenti Calcar,</hi> a freſh Gale, to him, that elſe would make the beſt of's way. The Merchant takes, or makes it ſo, who as he thrives makes every day a better Figure. At laſt, having improv'd the ſingle Talents he ſet up with, to five's, or ten's, it may be, five, or ten times told, lives up to all, and full out like himſelf. He might go cloath'd in Purple every day: nay, might wear Gold that wins it, ſaith our Proverb. But his Moderation in this, and all things, is well known to all Men. However in the modern Phraſe, <hi>He Lives well;</hi> he muſt, he can't be off on't. His general Acquaintance, particular Office, great Dealings as before, his obſervations, judgment and experience, his Correſpondence, and Intelligence make him a publick Good: Company often, and ſometimes Council for the Greateſt. As ſuch, he never wants Reſort, nor the Reſpects of Viſitants of good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; nor they a Welcom, and Reception ſuitable. Yet is it not the Noble Neceſſity thus laid upon him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49447:9"/> only, that obliges him to this, but he's as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of himſelf, and free, as forc't: hating with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous <hi>Job</hi> to eat his Sweet-meats by himſelf alone. Nor does his Hoſpitality abate his Charity, but aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it: and of his Fulneſs the Poor receive contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually to their no ſmall Comfort. How amply he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quites the good Offices of thoſe that have bin friendly, and faithful to him; eſpecially the Pains and Prayers of the ſedulous Watchman of his Soul: To what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, He relieves the oppreſt, and helpleſs, eſpecially the perſecuted for pure Conſcience ſake: what Sums he gives in all, to indigent Relations, which few great Merchants are without, eſpecially to the Induſtrious, that ſtrive to the utmoſt of their Strength, but againſt Stream, as Cramp't with too great Families, or ill Circumſtances, and muſt ſink irrecoverably without him: What his right hand does theſe wayes, his left, though elſe a boſom Friend, ſhall never know: No Eye but his, to whom all hearts are Open, and no Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets hid, ſhall ever ſee. Herein He is his own Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, while he lives: And that he may be ſo to all intents and purpoſes, where 'tis of higheſt Import to him, that he ſhould be ſo, that is, of his Laſt Will and Teſtament: He makes it in his beſt Health, while he has time to think of thoſe old <hi>Joſephs,</hi> whom his new Succeſſor would not know: And of the Poor, who, he <note place="margin">Exod. 1. 8.</note> Remember's are never to receive more from him, than he now bequeaths them. And to make all clear and well, makes uſe in this above all of Council. And thus, though dead, he yet ſpeaks, and acts, diſpoſes, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49447:10"/> diſtributes as much according to his mind, as if by his own Fire-ſide, and amongſt his old Friends ſtill. The ſuperlative Love he has had ever and in all places for the Honour, and Service of his King, and Country, make him extreamly dear to both. And this, together with the great plenty of the good things he enjoyes; and the far greater Pleaſure of doing the many good things he does, is what he made Account at firſt, ſhould make his Laſt days his Beſt: ſhould give his old Age a writ of Eaſe: his hoary Head a Bed of Honour: and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm his Name to all Poſterity.</p>
            <p>The good Chriſtian has his End too, but a glorious one, and high as Heaven it ſelf. Could he ſee Vertue in its Native Beauty and Brightneſs, 'twould need no Letters of Commendation to him. But ſince he wants thoſe Opticks, and ſees, and knows but in part, and that too imperfectly; he is allow'd to have regard, as well to the Price of his high Calling, as to the Race he is to run for't. 'Tis thought no diminution to a Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be a Fortune too. Nor is't to Piety that 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and has the Promiſes of both Lives. Nor does the great Apoſtle think our having thoſe Promiſes, too mean an Argument to move the beſt of us, <hi>to perfect holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> much leſs ſhould any think <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1.</note> the Examples he gives inſtance in, below our Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As of others, ſo of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who no minor, but when come to Age, refus'd the Crown of <hi>Egypt, and choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the People of God.</hi> For, he ſayes, <hi>He had reſpect to the recompence of Reward.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 24.</note> And of the bleſſed Jeſus himſelf, who, he ſays, <hi>endured</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49447:10"/> 
               <hi>the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, for the joy ſet before him.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 3.</note> With ſo good Reaſon, and in ſo good Company, the Chriſtian thinks He may very fairly have an Eye to both: not put aſunder what God himſelf has joyn'd together, the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof Of which vaſt Kingdom He is Heir in, and through Chriſt; looks for it, and in ſome meaſure lives up to it. He gets the Language of <hi>Canaan</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand; And puts on the Habit of the Country here: being cloth'd with Righteouſneſs, or rather cloth'd upon, with a much better, that of the Lord of Glory. His Houſe with reſpect to God is no other than an Oratory, or Temple ſanctified by the Word of God, which dwells richly there, and Prayer. And where every thing elſe is as it ſhould be, decent, and in Order. His Houſe with reſpect to Friends, is a ſpiritual St. <hi>Croſs</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>A Noble</hi> Hoſpital <hi>near</hi> Wincheſter.</note>. Where by the means of a good Conſcience, he keeps continual Feaſt; and where whoever would come, for a ſupply of thoſe wants, (which was the good-old-faſhion-End of Viſiting, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 16.) who would come might meet with ample Satisfaction. And where thoſe few that do come, are freely entertain'd with a Collation of his Travels, Trials, Conflicts and the Succeſſes he has had: Not to divert, ſo much as to direct, animate, and arm thoſe of like Occupation, and like enough to meet with all that he has paſt. He ſhews them, where they'l be moſt in danger to be impos'd upon: and where to be put to't: So, where their Skill, their Caution, their Courage, and Spiritual Armour, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49447:11"/> what of that, will be of moſt uſe to them. Shews them, how to deal with Men cunning to deceive: and how to defeat the devices of the Devil, of which he has a great many: and of which they had not need be ignorant. And ſhews them, how to hold faſt what they have got, that's good; that ſo no other take their Crown from them. Thus out of his own Stores he brings forth new, and old to thoſe will come for them. As often as he has the honour to be himſelf invited to his great Maſters Table, he's ſure to go: and there glad to ſee many a Brother and Companion he has had in tribulation, in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Patience of Jeſus Chriſt. More glad to ſee Him by Faith whom above all his Soul Loves. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, here 'tis, He chiefly taſtes, and ſees how good his Lord is. Is here careſſ'd with Chear above that of Angels, embrac'd with Armes of kindneſs, and aſſur'd of never, never-failing Favour: In the ſtrength <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5.</note> of which he walks comfortably many dayes after. And when to take his laſt long Journey, being firſt lighten'd by Confeſſion to, and Abſolution by his moſt affectionate and pious Paſtor; having the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Prayers of the Church more deeply ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cented by particular, and preſent Friends; And this Divine <hi>Viaticum,</hi> and Preſervative in ſtore, He doubts not to come ſafe and well to the end on't: and to the end withal, of all his Pains, and Patience, and be as happy as Heaven it ſelf can make him.</p>
            <p>Thus have you ſeen the Merchant, and in him, as in a Glaſs the Chriſtian in his Riſe, Progreſs, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49447:11"/> End. For your better Acquaintance, Pleaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him in ſome few of his Properties: not ſuch, as no other great Dealer has any thing of beſides: but ſuch as no Merchant is, or can be well without. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Prudence.</hi> This, like the Soul that animates, and acts him, is firſt, middle, laſt, and all in all in him. The true <hi>Gyges</hi> Ring, that penetrates moſt others Breaſts, but renders him, when-ever he thinks fit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. This firſt directs him to pitch on the moſt noble End: then to purſue it by the moſt proper means: and laſtly to ſecure the purchaſe of it. This makes him obſerve, and take time always by the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock: not come a day after the Fair, or ever overſtand his Market. Makes him enquire how Marts, and Matters go abroad; that he may know the better how to act at home. Makes him forecaſt all accidents, and do alwayes, what may turn to beſt account. Makes him to ſee and know himſelf what he deals in, and yet upon occaſion ask, and take advice too: eſpecially as to his Grand Purchaſe: where though he well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Particular himſelf; yet for the Clearneſs of the Title conſults the Learned in the Law, whoſe Talent lyes herein. The World is full of Cheats and Counterfeits: all is not Gold that Glitters, nor true Pearl neither that appears well. And as there's dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger all along, ſo without this, the Merchant may make Shipwrack in the very Port.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Chriſtian leſs a Man of Sence, or need he be. His being what he is; and doing what he does, is upon Choice not Chance. The Religion he eſpous'd betimes, and likes the better upon Uſe and Practice;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49447:12"/> He Profeſſes ſtill. Not becauſe 'tis the moſt faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, eaſie, or advantagious: but becauſe 'tis the beſt evidenc'd, refin'd, and rational. Free from the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality of the <hi>Jew,</hi> the Senceleſneſs of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and Senſuality of the <hi>Mahometan.</hi> The fitteſt to make him ſenſible of the Reſpects he owes to his Creatour, and Redeemer, his Fellow-Creatures, and himſelf. The fitteſt to exalt his Nature, perfect his Being, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign him to Rewards Infinite and Eternal. Nor will it let him ſpend his Money for that which is not Bread; on Pomp, and Pageantry; nor on an empty Noiſe, and next to Nothing: but on the real, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Truths of God, and Solid Reaſon, Meat indeed. This makes him enquire after, and pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which large Bottom his own Welfare is wound up. Makes him foreſee an Evil, and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſhift it, or the more bravely bear up againſt it. Makes him, though not for an implicit Faith, yet for more Satisfaction as to his Title to Heaven to call for, and conſult his Spiritual Guide, whom, as continually attending upon this very thing, he knows Able, and in whom, upon all the many occaſions he has had, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with him, He has always found the Grace, to be Faithful.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Juſtice.</hi> 'Tis the part of this to give every one his due, and this the Merchant makes it his Buſineſs punctually to do. To God above, in being True to his Religion, at all times, and in all places. <hi>Coelum, non animum mutat.</hi> Not turning like his Flags, and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, with every Wind: Nor Changing the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of his Conſcience, as the <hi>Cameleon,</hi> Colour;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49447:12"/> with every Country he ſets his feet upon. He's true to his Devotions at Land, as well as Sea, When Safe, as when in Danger. No more robs God of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or Offerings, in Filching Tythes: than <hi>Caeſar</hi> of his Tribute, and Cuſtoms in Running Goods. He won't ſet out without his Paſtors Prayers, nor returns without Acknowledging the Benefit of them. Is true and juſt, as he is timely taught, in all his Dealings with all Men. Falſe Weights, and Meaſures he abhor's: His are full out Statute, and Standard: Nor does he buy, and ſell by different, but the ſame. In buying, he bids in reaſonable Proportion to the Worth: in ſelling asks not unreaſonably out of the Way. Nor is ever ſo faſt ty'd, as when left at Liberty to ſet his own Price. If He know any damage, or defect, he tells it: or He ſells it ſo much the Cheaper: But what you have his honeſt Word upon, you need no other Warrant for.</p>
            <p>And ſuch every way in the ſame Relations is the good Chriſtian. Adores his Maker's Greatneſs, and admires his Mercy: Gives His Commandments due Obedience; his Promiſes Faith, and full Aſſurance; and in all Attributes does him right. What no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Perſon can be, that the good Chriſtian is to the full, that is, a Good Subject to his Prince. The Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are ready to Run, before Routed, and flee when none purſues: And their very Prayers are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſays the ſame <hi>Solomon:</hi> So can neither Fight for the King, nor Pray for him as they ought. Whereas the Good Chriſtian, that has no Reaſon to fear Death in a good Cauſe, and has a conſiderable Intereſt in the Court of Heaven, always does the one, and is always
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49447:13"/> ready to do the other. And is ſo free both to Aſſociate with, and Aſſiſt thoſe, that do, that proves his Prince bears Rule not ſo much over him, as in him. His Miniſter he reſpects, and loves both for his Maſter's, and his Work's ſake: Encourages by Conſtant Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, early Appearance, and Candid Audience, and maintains him above the rate of Cummin, Mint, and Anniſe. In all his Dealings with all men, he conſiders the Character he bears: and though he buy of a <hi>Turk,</hi> and ſell to a <hi>Jew,</hi> He remembers ſtill, he is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and muſt, and will be juſt, and Upright.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Complacent and obliging Temper, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour. No wonder a Veſſel full of Liquor boils over with froth, and fury, when either a ſtrong fire is round it, or a ferment as fierce within it. Nor is it ſtranger, if any in uneaſie Circumſtances, be, or behave themſelves accordingly. In Men ſenſibly decaying, in debt, in pain, or paſſion, diſgrace, or diſcontent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable of any ſort, who runs may read their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, in ſudden Sighs, ſower Faces, ſnappiſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and convulſive Motions. But the Merchant <hi>Indoeilis pauperiem pati,</hi> Untaught ill Nature by any Ill Succeſſes, or ill Uſage, who flows in Wealth, and has the World at will, that's all Serene, and calm within, and ſoft, and ſmooth without is eaſie to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and eaſie to all others. Eaſie to be ſpoke with: and eaſie to be ſpoke to. And as eaſily, and freely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, aſſiſts, and acts a friends part, on any call; on any occaſion whatſoever. Takes every thing that's offer'd with <hi>Epictetus,</hi> by the right handle; and in all doubtful Caſes, has a Comment of kindneſs always
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49447:13"/> ready. He is indeed Sweetneſs, and Candor, Reſpect, and Generoſity in the very Abſtract: nor is he ever more himſelf than while exerting theſe, or moſt of theſe.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Chriſtians Religion an Enemy to Good Manners; Nor He any of thoſe that pleaſe not God; and yet in this Reſpect, are contrary to all other Men. Much leſs an Enemy to good Nature: For 'tis the very deſign of it, to make him all ſuch: To ſweeten his Bloud and Spirits, to mollify, and meliorate his Temper, and whole Conſtitution. To down with every turbulent and topping Humour: to Up with every root of Bitterneſs within him: to out and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board with all Pride and Paſſion, lying and ſlandering; with all malice, and revenge; To be meek, and lowly; to be cloth'd, or grac'd rather, with Humility. To be <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 5. <hi>from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>nodus ad orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </note> pittiful; to be courteous; to be kindly affectioned one to another in brotherly Love; and in honour prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one another. To be ready to diſtribute; and do all good Offices for all Orders, and degrees of Men, as opportunity is offer'd, eſpecially to the Houſhold of Faith. If Temptation, or Loſs happen, through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, not his fault, he's taught to take it patiently, not be diſturb'd himſelf, or trouble others, as if ſome ſtrange thing had happened to him, or never any ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row were like his. If Reproach or Slander come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſervedly upon him, He ſhakes it off as unconcern'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Viper, into the ſame fire from whence it came. Indeed, wherever the Chriſtian Religion comes, and makes a Conqueſt over any perſon; in whom ſoever it has its perfect work; it transforms
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49447:14"/> him wholly by the Renewing of his Mind, ſo that then and thenceforth he <hi>ſuffers long; is kind; envies not; vaunts not himſelf; is not puft up; behaves himſelf no wayes unſeemly; ſeeks not his own; is not eaſily provok't; thinks no evil; rejoices not in Iniquity, but in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Truth; bears all things, believes all things; hopes all things; endures all things.</hi> And this it never failes <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 4. <hi>to</hi> 10.</note> to do; nor ever therefore failes to make the Chriſtian the beſt Pariſhioner, Houſe-keeper, Husband, Father, Maſter, Neighbour, Friend, and Enemy (if he can be made one) in all the World beſides.</p>
            <p>Thus runs the parallel betwixt the Merchant, and the Chriſtian upon the account of ſome of his many good Properties: it might be drawn to a much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Length; but that 'tis more than time, I drew to a Concluſion. Upon the whole then, be we all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to Conſider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Who we are:</hi> Chriſtians, and Merchant-like Men.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Where we are:</hi> Abroad, and far from Home.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>What we have to do:</hi> Make ſure our All.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Let the firſt of theſe induce Us to <hi>walk worthy of the vocation, whereby we are called;</hi> at leaſt do nothing dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to it. Some Merchants have bin Princes; and ſome Princes are Merchants ſtill. <hi>Alexander</hi> would not enter the Liſts at the <hi>Olympicks,</hi> becauſe there were no Kings to enter with him. And ſhall the bare thought of being of ſuch a Sex, and not the ſtronger neither, be able to ſecure one half the World from Indecency, and open ill? and ſhall not all the Reaſon, and Religion in the World be able to ſecure the other? Our Light ſhould ſo ſhine, it ſhould be ſeen; And men Glorify
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49447:14"/> our Founder, and our Faith too, for our Works ſake. See how they Live! See how they Love! ſaid the old Heathens of the firſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Let the ſecond oblige us to take the Renowned <hi>Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leighs</hi> advice to a young Noble about to travel. <hi>A cloſe Mouth: An open Eye: A ſmooth Forehead,</hi> Let not our Tongues betray us into trouble; nor be we buſy med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in others matters, but mind our own. Let us prevent ſurpriſe; and not think to ſay too late. Alas! who would have thought it? And let them hang the head, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the halter; The Chriſtian that is all peace, and joy within, ſhould keep continual Jubilee; Chear up, and look to Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And let the third and laſt Conſideration prevail upon us to ſecure our All: our Heaven, and everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. The little All we are call'd to do, and can do, let us up, and be doing. Walk, and not be weary, run and not faint. Follow our works for a ſhort time; and our works ſhall follow us to an endleſs and bleſſed Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Here 'tis, indeed, that the Chriſtian has the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Merchant. In the nature, and ſo value of the things they deal in and for. The Merchant is for <hi>Cedar, Ivory,</hi> and <hi>Arras;</hi> for <hi>Mettles, Spices, Jewels;</hi> the rich Furniture of others, and his own houſe: The Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and well-being but of the Body at beſt. The Chriſtian is for what, nor Moth, nor Ruſt will touch, nor Thief can take; the Ornament of a meek, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Spirit: and the Salvation of his immortal Soul. So, In the manner of their reſpective dealing. The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant muſt go, and come, muſt tread the Wine-preſs alone, do his buſineſs himſelf, or 'twill go on but heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49447:15"/> or not at all. The Chriſtian has great Aſſiſtance, and helps for his Infirmities. Has his works done in and for him; and his ſtrength is in a manner to ſit ſtill. But above all that is, or might be ſaid, in the general Iſſue and Event of all at laſt; the Merchant is an Adventurer, the Chriſtian on a ſure Foundation: the Merchant may loſe much, loſe all he has, nay loſe himſelf after all. But the good Chriſtian except he will himſelf, can never loſe his Aim. Let him be diligent and he ſhall thrive, and proſper in the inner man, and <hi>add daily to his Faith, Vertue</hi> Let him commit the keeping of his Soul to God, none ſhall pluck it out of his hand; it ſhall be ſafe. Let him continue in well-doing to the End, and he ſhall have his long wiſht End too, and be happy. Totally happy; his Body freed from all diſtempers, and defects: his mind from all diſſatisfaction and diſeaſe. His Body ſo far ſpiritualiz'd at leaſt, as never more to need to ſue for Alimony but be made like his Saviours glorious Body. His Soul partaker of the Divine Nature; as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, equal to Angels: nay according to their Model, God-like, perfectly happy, and Eternally happy. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifi'd in all their Powers, and Faculties firſt, and then fill'd over, and ever fill'd with Joy unſpeakable, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and wonder Everlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God who declareſt thy Almighty power moſt chiefly in ſhewing Mercy and Pity: Mercifully Grant unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, ſuch a meaſure of thy Grace, that we running the way of thy Commandments, may obtain thy gracious promiſes, and be made partakers of thy heavenly Treaſure, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
